Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be learning
about oxidation reduction reactions.
Now, what makes oxidation so
excited is that it's something
that is around our entire world.
So it allows us to function.
It's what allows the entire world to work.
Well, we can see it around us.
If you go outside, right, you see that
the different plants that are around
you are going through photosynthesis.
This is a process of oxidation.
You right now are functioning
via oxidation reduction.
Your digestive system, your, the cellular
respiration that's occurring inside of
you, your metabolism, all of these are
all working through oxidation reduction.
Now when it comes to other reactions
that are occurring as well that you
see around you, you being able to watch
me right now, it's probably thanks to
oxidation reduction, especially if you're
on a laptop, a cell phone, a tablet.
All these different devices are
powered via batteries, which are
constantly all about this process.
Now, what is it?
Well, oxidation reduction is also
commonly known as a redox reaction.
And all it is, is how electrons are
going to be moving in between atoms.
So when we are trying to look at
this, we are going to be seeing
how electrons can be transferred
from one species to another.
to the other.
And this is going to be
the entire idea here.
So when we're looking at this,
well, we can explain it through some
simple ideas is that oxidation is
all about the loss of an electron.
Reduction is all about the gain of
electron, which can sound a little
confusing when you think about reduction.
It's like, how's it gaining
when it sounds like deuce.
So we'll talk about that here in a
second, but let's just go back to just
trying to label our little atoms here.
And how exactly can we
label each of these species?
Well, which one of these, uh, within
every oxidation reduction reaction,
there are always a pair, meaning that
if one species is being oxidized,
The other one must be reduced.
So being that we have on the left here,
we have a is giving away an electron.
It's being donated to another species
or a K it's losing its electron.
You can see on the left,
we have that is being.
oxidized.
And now on the right hand side, well,
being that you see that B is receiving
that electron, this is being reduced.
So this is all we are
trying to see in this video.
And through trying to understand
this is where can you see the hidden
chemistry occurring within a reaction?
Sometimes you might only see,
it looks like a normal single
displacement reaction, a normal
combustion reaction, but there's
something hidden behind the scenes.
Hidden within the charges or the oxidation
numbers of these different species.
And that's what we're
going to be seeing today.
We're going to be learning exactly
what this means and how it is that
we can understand the different
phrases that we're going to see.
Let's take a look at a little
bit of all of this together.
Now trying to keep oxidation reduction
straight can be extremely tough.
Well how do you know which is which?
Well oxidation loss of electron,
reduction gain of electron, that
doesn't really quite make sense.
Well, the first thing is
trying to understand reduction,
right, gaining an electron.
Well, where does the
word reduce come from?
Well, the way that we got to look
at that, it's all about how we
are reducing the charge, right?
Whenever you are gaining an electron,
you got to remember that the number
is going down, down, down, down,
down is becoming more negative
because electrons are the more you
add, the more negative it becomes.
Which is the idea here, right?
It's all about trying to change it.
So what it all comes down to is trying
to remember, trying to remember little
cute mnemonics for you to never forget
oxidation reduction because this
is a phrase that you will need for
chemistry, for biology, for physiology,
for biochemistry, for all these other
courses in it because it's so important.
So remember the phrase Leo goes grr.
which you will never forget what
it means for oxidation production.
So Leo, Leo, the lion, loss
of electron is oxidation.
Okay.
Loss of electrons.
is oxidation.
So where does the Leo part come from?
Well, if I just kind of underline
that for us, we got loss, uh, the
loss of electrons is oxidation.
And that's where that is coming from.
Now, the other one, which is
reduction is gain of electrons.
In electron is reduction, so loss electron
oxidation in of electron is reduction.
So Leo goes, Grr, is the way that
we are going to remember this.
So all you got to do is remember how a
line is growling at you are goring and
you'll never forget that little phrase
to help you be able to label these.
And that's what we're going to do.
Through this actual chemical
reaction, let's take a look.
All right, so in our first example,
what we are going to be doing
is labeling oxidation states.
So what an oxidation state is a way
for us to essentially do some electron
bookkeeping to determine where are the
electrons moving within the reaction.
They do not always represent the
actual charges, but they do tell us
what kind of chemistry is occurring.
So the first thing is, is being able
to tell the difference between ionic
compounds and atomically neutral
elements and compounds in these
different molecules that we'll see.
So first is as I have sodium
and chlorine and they are
combining together to make NaCl.
So what I have here is I have
two different species over here.
These are different atomic species
that if you remember from your periodic
table are inherently neutral, okay?
So being that these are neutral, what
oxidation state could we give them?
Well, they're both going to
have an oxidation state of zero.
So when you have a pure substance
or a diatomic gas that exists in its
natural state, they have what we refer
to as an oxidation state of zero.
Now the only difference between oxidation
state and ionic charge is that ionic
charge is the real, is the actual
charge of losing and gaining electrons.
This is very similar, but we use
different terminology to describe it.
So on the right hand side,
I have an ionic compound.
Meaning that there are charges, which
we can use the charges to tell us
what are the actual oxidation states.
So if you remember sodium has a plus one
charge, chlorine has a minus one charge.
So what this can help us see is,
well, what species is being oxidized?
which one is being produced.
So the way that we can look at this
is by observing something and looking
at what we call a half reaction.
What a half reaction it does is
you write down the species from
the left and the right side.
So I have sodium on the left
and it has a charge of zero.
And it's going to be turning in
to sodium on the right hand side.
Where it's going to be changing
its charge to a plus one, so
it's going from NA0 to plus.
Now the question is, is this gaining
an electron, or is it losing?
Is it Leo goes Grr?
Being that our charge is, in this
case, it's becoming more positive,
so we are losing an electron in the
process, so what we can see is here is
that, oh, okay, well sodium is being.
Oxidized.
Therefore, meaning that chlorine,
on the other hand, must be reduced.
Remember, they're a pair, so you cannot,
they each have to do their own unique.
Now, how can we show that?
Well, if I write down the charges
for chlorine, it's going from a
zero to a negative one charge,
meaning it's gaining an electron.
The charge is being reduced and
becoming more and more negative, and
we're gaining an electron as a result.
So, is this the only thing I
can show in this half reaction?
Well, we can illustrate that the
electron is being gained as well.
One thing you may have noticed
is that I was writing down the
symbol E with a minus next to it.
That's referring to that we have
an electron that's being gained.
So what I can do is write
E minus plus chlorine zero.
And what we're trying to do is balance the
charges on the two sides of the reaction.
And that's it.
Notice how on the left side, I have a
total of minus one, and on the right
side, I also have a total minus one.
Now, this one on the
bottom shows reduction.
On the top, oxidation should be the
opposite, showing the loss of an electron.
Electron being, being
essentially sent away.
So what we can, how we can show
that is, well, if I have a zero
charge on the left hand side of
this, of this half reaction up top.
I should also have a zero up here, so it's
plus one plus negative one, which means
I have to put my electron on the right.
This is one of the ideas, what we try
to show with oxidation reduction, how
the electrons are being transferred.
Uh, when we have essentially a
sodium, it's giving away, in this
case it's going to be giving away its
electron to a chlorine, so it's being
transferred from one to the other.
So we can show how that electron
will be transferred, which makes
sense if you think about it, right?
Sodium naturally has a plus one charge,
so it's going to try to give its electron
a chlorine so it can bond and react.
So Leo goes Grr.
Let's look at some other examples to
keep further our understanding here.
Before we go into our examples, the
first thing I should do is establish
these little rules for you to be
able to label your oxidation states.
Now for right now, this is an
introduction to redox reactions.
So we're just gonna look at a
very simple set of rules that get
us through the basics for now.
So the first thing is, is whenever
you have a pure element or a natural
state of an element, like a diatomic
or sulfur, which exists as S eight
or phosphorus, which has P four,
these are always have a charge zero.
Or even if you have like a metal that's
by itself, meaning it's not ionic.
It's not bound to something.
It's just alone.
So whenever that happens,
it has a charge of zero.
Now the other species are, well, if you
have a cat ion or an anion within an ionic
compound, They will, their charge will
equal your oxidation state, they will be
the same number, which is good, right?
It's like, Oh, that's one thing
that we really need for ourselves.
Make it easier.
The other thing that's important
is being that if you remember ionic
compounds are overall neutral, it applies
the same here with oxidation states.
The sum of the positives and negative
half that you have to cancel, meaning
it has to equal zero, which is extremely
important to see in these problems.
Let's take a look.
So our first example here what we are
going to be looking at is assigning the
oxidation states Based on the simple rules
that we said before and keep in mind We're
just going to do a simple introduction
of labeling oxidation reduction.
So we're not going to be doing
complete Complete redox reactions.
So the first part is that we have iron
which is in its natural state Meaning
that it's going to have a charge of zero
next to the molecule, or next to the atom.
And that's going to be combining with two
chlorine atoms, or the diatomic, which
means it's also in its natural state.
And we're going to assign that as a zero.
Now, on our ionic compound, we
are going to use our reverse
swap drop to be able to see this.
Well, if you remember, chlorine
always has a charge of negative one.
Meaning that if there's three of
them total, so the total negative
is three minus, so what does the
overall charge of iron have to be?
Well, to balance that out, it
must be a charge of three plus.
So we are going to put that charge right
next to it, three plus, to help illustrate
that we have our oxidation state as
three plus and one minus for chlorine.
and iron.
So now what we can do is we can label
what our half reactions are, label what's
being oxidized, what's being reduced here.
So on our first one, we have iron
is turning in to iron 3 plus.
So is this going to be gaining or
losing electrons in the process?
Well, we have that there are three less
electrons on the right, meaning it's
going to be losing three electrons.
So if we are losing three
electrons, what are we doing?
Well, if you remember, Leo goes
grr, so we are going to be oxidized.
In this case, iron is oxidized,
which just means it's rusting.
Now on our other one, we have chlorine.
We have Cl2 is going to be falling
apart into two chlorine ions, and that
has a zero charge and a minus charge.
Well, how can we go through
and balance this one out?
Well, this one's a little bit different,
is being that I had to add a coefficient
here to balance out the charge, because
we had, or balance out the, the atoms,
being that we have a 2 on the left,
we will have a total of 2 electrons
that have to be gained to balance out
the overall 2 charge on the right.
So we have our oxidation
reduction process.
We're gaining electrons on the bottom.
And losing electrons on that's
one of the ideas when we're
writing our half reactions.
Now let's look at trying to just
practice assigning oxidation states.
So when you're practicing these, sometimes
you might have to fill in a table just
like the one here, which is all about
can you just quickly assign these because
you want it to be second nature to you.
So the first one is P4.
Now this one I picked because it's
a little bit of a strange one.
It is actually the natural
state of phosphorus.
There's some other weird ones you
might see as well, which are like S8,
for example, are the natural state.
So other than the diatomics,
these are some other ones when
they are in their natural state.
So let's say if I have phosphorus four,
they're going to have a charge of zero for
all the phosphoruses that are available.
Same thing with sulfur S8.
They are going to have a charge of zero.
Now on the next one we have
K2O, so potassium oxide.
So how would we end up assigning that?
So let's write down our species.
Well being that this is an ionic
compound, right, a metal and a
nonmetal, we will assign our charges
like normal for our oxidation states.
So we have two minus and then one
plus for our oxidation states.
So they are going to be the
same as the ionic charge.
Same thing with barium
chloride on the next one.
We have barium and then we have chlorine.
Well, chlorine always has a ionic charge
of negative one, so that means it's going
to have a oxidation state of one minus.
Same with barium as well.
It has a plus two charge
for ionic charges.
Meaning it's going to be a two plus
charge for the oxidation number.
Now for iron, well, iron is
right now in its natural state.
It's referring to just
the metal by itself.
So what's the charge going to be?
It's going to be zero versus
the one that's below it.
We have iron two plus, so it's charge
is also going to be, or it's oxidation
state is also going to be two plus.
It's going to be the same
general idea when we are looking
through, looking at these.
different molecules and trying
to see, okay, how is the
oxidation state and the charges?
How are they going to line up?
The last one is O2.
Well, O2 is the natural
state of it, right?
It's what you're breathing right now.
So O2 is going to have a charge zero.
So this is how we can practice it, right?
It's the same as your charges.
The only difference is that they're
called oxidation states and it's more
for how are the electrons moving?
Let's look at one last example.
So practicing as quick as we
can, can we identify what's being
oxidized, what's being reduced?
Let's label our charges.
So with K2O on the left, your oxidation
state for potassium is plus one, your
oxidation state for oxygen is two minus.
Now on the right hand side, being
that we have four potassiums that are
by themselves, this is going to be
a natural element that's all alone.
It's gonna have a zero charge.
Same thing with your diatomic oxygen.
It's going to have a mine or have a
zero charge because it is by itself.
When we're trying to label
these, we have potassium.
It's gone from a plus to a zero.
So where is the, is electrons
being gained or is it being lost?
Well, we can see that the
charge is being reduced.
It's becoming more negative that
we can write that we are gaining an
electron that we are being produced.
So GRR part.
And then with oxygen, we have O2 minus.
Is, and we have two of them on this,
in this case, it's going to become
O2, that's going to a zero charge.
So we can see that, oh, well, we're going
to be losing in this case, four electrons
are going to be lost or oxidized.
That's the basic idea of looking
at oxidation reduction is how many
electrons are being gained, how
many are being lost, which is all
we need to know for introductory
chemistry for the fundamentals.
There will be future videos on oxidation
reduction, it's something that will come
back, and when we go over harder type of
reactions later, um, in future videos.
So, please don't forget about how
all this works, and I hope this
video helped you understand that
electrons are transferred in reactions.
Um, especially when you're looking
at single replacement reactions
and combustion reactions, there
are electrons being transferred.
All right.
Thank you so much for listening.
And if it's your first time here, please
hit that like and subscribe button and
hit that comment below what you thought.
And thank you so much for, for being
here and I really appreciate it.
And I hope you all have a wonderful day.
Bye now.